בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is officially מ"ח, Mem Chet,
48, but we are a bit behind, so hopefully we'll catch up
this morning. We start on מ"ז עמוד א', Mem Zayin Amud Aleph,
not working there, מ"ז עמוד א', Mem Zayin Amud Aleph,
and near the bottom of מ"ז עמוד א', Mem Zayin Amud Aleph,
we had been discussing this issue about that if the mother is
a בת לוי Bat Levi or בת כהן, Bat Kohen, which actually
is being called here לויה Leviyah and כהנת, Kohenet, that the child
is exempt from פדיון הבן, Pidyon HaBen, and there are two explanations.
One is only in the very rare case that the father is
not Jewish, because if the father is Jewish, then the child's identity
goes after the father, but if the father is not Jewish, to
some degree it would be defined by the mother, and actually if
he has a Jewish mother and a non-Jewish father, he would be
a quasi or a פסול לוי, Pasul Levi, but that לוי Levi
identification would be enough to exempt from פדיון הבן, Pidyon HaBen, and
therefore it's defined though the exemption is defined by the child. And
then we had the opinion, which is the one we rule by,
of in the name of רבא, Rava, which is that no, even
if it's a Jewish father, it's not from the child's identity as
כהן Kohen or לוי, Levi, but it's sufficient that the mother is
a בת כהן Bat Kohen or בת לוי, Bat Levi, כהנת Kohenet
and לויה, Leviyah, because it goes by פטר רחם Peter Rechem and
the mother's status matters here.
Did he get מעשר? Ma'aser?
No, nobody according to the first explanation, that's a good question, it's
not really explored and we never find that anywhere else, so I
would have to say, I would have to say no, although the
גמרא Gemara does say לוי פסול, Levi Pasul,
you know, it's hard to even call him a לוי Levi because
his father isn't a לוי. Levi. So one has to assume it
means that there's some quasi לוי Levi status, we never would have
found anybody suggesting that that, you know, that you would give like
מעשר Ma'aser to that person.
But the boys so showed had an excellent question yesterday after the
class.
Go, you had a question,
what you said after the class.
Oh, about about what happens nowadays if somebody dies and they take
it to a בית דין. Beis Din. Yeah, well actually that's a
very good, in theory the answer should be yes, if that's why
everybody's encouraged to write a halachic will, you know, halachic will, that's
right, but if somebody didn't write a halachic will and let's say
they brought it in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to a, you see,
I don't think in the states if you bring it to a
בית דין Beis Din that that can override the laws of inheritance.
But it can if both parties
agree to it, yeah, but you'd have to be pretty stupid to
agree to that. No, but if in Israel for example, I really
wonder what they would do in that case. All right, so anyway
let's continue. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, so תנן, Tnan, three lines down in the wide lines, מי
שהיו לו בנים ונשא אשה שלא ילדה. Mi shehayu lo banim venasa
ishah shelo yaldah. So this is our משנה. Mishna. Somebody had children
and married a woman who had not had children, so it's going
to be a case of not a firstborn for inheritance because the
man had already had children, but it will be for the כהן
Kohen for פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. נתגיירה ומעוברת נשתחררה ומעוברת, Nisgayerah u'meuberet
nishcharah u'meuberet, or a woman converted when she was pregnant, freed when
she was pregnant, וילדה, veyaldah, and she gave birth, so that type
of a case, the child is born as it's born as a
firstborn for this for this woman, so therefore it is a פטר
רחם Peter Rechem for the woman and therefore what do you call
it, and therefore firstborn for the פדיון. Pidyon.
היא וכהנת היא ולויה היא ואשה שכבר ילדה, Hi vekohenet hi veleviyah
hi veishah shekvar yaldah, or let's say the child got mixed up
between her and the daughter of and the child of her son
and the son of somebody who had already had children, so you
don't know which one is חייב בפדיון הבן, chayav bepidyon haben, or
her son and the son of a כהנת Kohenet or the son
of a לויה, Leviyah, that's going to be the case we're going
to focus on, right, and which are also not חייב בפדיון הבן.
chayav bepidyon haben. So you don't know definitely her son is obligated
in פדיון הבן, Pidyon HaBen, you just don't know which one is
her son. Okay, that's the scenario. וכן מי שלא שהתה אחר בעלה
שלשה חדשים, Vechen mi shelo shahah acharei ba'alah sheloshah chodashim, or somebody
that whose husband died and got remarried within three months, וניסת וילדה,
veniset veyaldah, and then
she got remarried in those three months had a child, you don't
know who is the father. So in all those cases you don't
know
he does not get the inheritance firstborn because you don't know who
the father is.
But wherever he is, he's obligated in פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen even
if and therefore there will be a פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen whichever
one of these two is my son, I'm doing a פדיון הבן
Pidyon HaBen for him. Okay, so those are the scenarios. We're not
going to unpack them fully, what we are going to focus on,
thank you, is that one of the cases is what do you
call it, one of the cases is her son which is חייב
בפדיון הבן chayav bepidyon haben gets mixed up with the son of
a כהנת Kohenet or לויה. Leviyah. So in our משנה Mishna it's
very clear that a son of a כהנת Kohenet or לויה Leviyah
is exempt from פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen and the right, so you
get it, the point in our משנה Mishna is one of them
is obligated, you don't know which one, so you as the father
still have to do פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen whichever whichever one of
these two is your sons, you just don't know which one it
is. So anyway it's clear that the son of a כהנת Kohenet
or לויה Leviyah is exempt from פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay, so מכלל דכהנת, Michlal dekohenet, from here you see to כהנת,
Kohenet, actually this I just I skipped the upshot of that. I'm
sorry, just I last I I skipped the upshot of that. בכור
לכהן Bechor le-kohen in all these cases it's חייב בפדיון chayav be-pidyon
ואין בכור לנחלה, ve-ein bechor le-nachala, not for the inheritance because you
don't know who the father is.
You covered it.
What? I covered it? I didn't read it. Okay anyway, מכלל michlal
from that you see דכהנת ולויה פטורה de-kohenet u-leviyah ptura
that the child of a כהנת kohenet and a לויה leviyah is
exempt. It's explicit in our משנה. mishnah. And so now let's understand
that. Okay fine, that's what we've been saying. Now let's try to
understand. דאיעבר ממאן? di-avar mi-man? Who's the father? אילמא דאיעבר מכהן ולוי,
ileima di-avar mi-kohen ve-Levi, if it's a כהן kohen and a לוי
Levi who's the father, so אי הכי מה איריא כהנת ולויה? i-hachi
mai irya kohenet ve-leviyah? Even a בת ישראל נמי? bat Yisrael nami?
You don't have to say a כהנת kohenet or לויה, leviyah, right,
didn't you just say that the wife of a כהן kohen or
the wife of a לוי? Levi? So you say כהנת ולויה, kohenet
ve-leviyah, it sounds that the exemption comes from the mother's identity as
a כהנת kohenet or לויה. leviyah. So אלא דאיעבר מעובדי כוכבים. ella
di-avar mi-ovdei kochavim.
So it's like we've been saying, the father is a non-Jew. So
that, now we've got a problem, right, because until now we've had
two explanations when a כהנת kohenet and a לויה leviyah would be
exempt. One is they're just straight exempt because it goes by the
mother as well and even and her status is enough to exempt,
that's what we rule. And the other is no, it's only when
the father is a non-Jew, non-Jew, so the child's status is quasi-follows
the mother. So we've been talking about a case of a לויה
leviyah up until now, but now the reason the גמרא gemara brought
in our משנה mishnah is because you can't have that explanation by
a כהנת kohenet because what will happen, can anybody think where the
גמרא gemara is going with this? What will happen if it's a
בת כהן bat kohen that has had sex with a non-Jew? Any
thoughts? She will, she, that she will lose her כהונה kehuna status,
her status.
Therefore, we can't be talking about the non-Jew scenario because if a
woman, we'll see in a minute, if a woman has, this actually
is one of the real major challenges nowadays, you know, for כהנים,
kohanim, as if they didn't have it hard enough, with the issues
of גרושה grusha or whatever, which is is that if the woman,
let's say is בעל תשובה ba'al teshuva or or for or whatever,
just, you know, has gone to college and has had a period
of experimenting, whatever, and has had sex with a non-Jew, she's אסור
assur to a כהן. kohen. So
she cannot marry a כהן. kohen. So if this...
a כהן kohen today has to marry a virgin?
No, but she cannot have had sex with a non-Jew, with somebody
because one of the definitions, the way the רמב"ם Rambam frames it
is that the תורה Torah's definition of זונה, zona, so is not
literally prostitute but has to do with an act of sex which
could not have been in a marital context. And therefore since marriage
is not possible with a non-Jew, that that therefore that woman becomes
forbidden to a כהן. kohen. But she can have sex with a
Jew outside of marriage with a Jew.
So it has to do with עריות, arayot, right?
We're not going to talk about that now, but that, the question
of the way the... sometimes this is dealt with has to do
with right, about whether she explicitly, who, like who, you know, do
you have... who's believed about those things in order to create an
objective reality to create that problem? But we won't go into that
right now, but it's along the path that you mentioned. So anyway,
so because of that...
it's basically like a כהן kohen marrying a גרושה, grusha, it's the
same thing. אסור. assur. Right. And your סמיכה s'micha is gone.
Yes, these are clear איסורים. issurim. Yes. Alright. So now the גמרא
gemara goes on and says the following.
So let's take a look. So anyway, one of the cases is
כהנת. kohenet. So if you say it's a non-Jew,
so כהנת פטורה? kohenet ptura? Will she be a כהן kohen to
have an exempt status? והא אמר רב פפא, ve-ha amar Rav Pappa,
רב פפא Rav Pappa said, בדק לן רבה, badka lan Rabbah, רבה
Rabbah or רבא Rava some say, tested us. It's an interesting thing,
like he was giving us a quiz, wanted to see, you know,
how sharp we were. And he asked us the following question. כהנת
שנתעברה מעובדי כוכבים מהו? kohenet she-nit'abra mi-ovdei kochavim mahu? If a כהן,
kohen, a בת כהן bat kohen has a child from a non-Jew,
goes, is pregnant, what's the story for פדיון הבן? pidyon haben? ואמינא
ליה אנא, ve-amina lei ana, and I said to him, לאו היינו
דרב אדא בר אהבה דאמר לויה שילדה בנה פטור מחמישה סלעים? lav
hainu de-Rav Adda bar Ahava de-amar leviyah she-yaleda bena patur me-chamisha sela'im?
Isn't that what we just said yesterday? That if a לויה leviyah
has a child from a non-Jew, the child is you know, if
a לויה leviyah has a child, her son is exempt, at least
one interpretation said that it was because she had a child from
a non-Jew. So wasn't that the case?
So it should be the same if it's a כהן, kohen, בת
כהן. bat kohen. So he says no. So you failed the test
because it's not the same. So he says, where were we? ואמר
לי, ve-amar li, he said back to me, הכי השתא? hachi hashta?
How can you compare them? בשלמא לויה בקדושתה קיימא. bishlama leviyah bikdushata
kaima. If a בת לוי bat Levi has sex with a non-Jew,
it doesn't affect her status. Nobody said it was מותר, mutar, but
it doesn't affect her status. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
baraita, לויה שנשבית, leviyah she-nishbeita, if a בת לוי, bat Levi, a
לויה leviyah is taken captive, או שנבעלה בעילת זנות, o she-nivala be'ilat
zenut, and when she's taken captive you assume that she was raped,
or that she actually just had sex with out of marriage and
with even presumably with a non-Jew is the context here. Nevertheless, נותנין
לה מעשר ואוכלת, notnin lah ma'aser ve-ochelet, you can still give her
מעשר, ma'aser, she doesn't lose her לוי Levi status. By the way,
very interesting because you remember when we learned מתנות כהונה matnot kehuna
we learned that you can give מתנות כהונה matnot kehuna directly to
a בת כהן, bat kohen, they used the phrase כהנת kohenet there
too, and that was unusual. Because normally we don't call, the very
fact that I have to be constantly translating this בת כהן Bat
Cohen is because the whole phrase כהנת cohenet for us is an
unusual concept, that of the woman herself has that identity. But it
actually is true for those מתנות כהונה, matnos kehuna, זרוע, לחיים, וקיבה,
zero'a, lechayayim, v'keiva, it's true also for a בת לוי Bat Levi
for מעשר, maaser, you can give it straight to a בת לוי,
Bat Levi, as if she's directly entitled to it. Okay. And therefore
it's telling us that that status is not affected by the fact
that she has had sex with a non-Jew. That's for a בת
לוי. Bat Levi. Then I can understand if her child from the
non-Jew has a quasi-Levi status. However,
אלא כהנת, ela cohenet, but a
כהנת, cohenet, כיון דנבעלה, keivan d'niv'ala, if she has sex with a
non-Jew, הויא זרה, havya zara, she is a זרה, zara, she means
she loses all of her כהונה kehuna status. Now actually, as I
said before, it's even true that a ישראלית Yisraelit who had sex
with a non-Jew is אסורה לכהן. asura l'kohein. But for a ישראלית,
Yisraelit, all that means is that she's forbidden for a כהן. kohein.
For a כהנת, cohenet, the same thing that makes her that would
make even if she was a ישראלית Yisraelit forbidden to a כהן
kohein means that it's a contradiction to the whole כהונה, kehuna, the
whole כהונה kehuna status and that's why she's forbidden. So therefore if
she is a כהנת, cohenet, it undermines her identity as a בת
כהן Bat Cohen and therefore she can no longer, it would not,
the child would not have a quasi-Cohen status. Tosafot over there also
points out that you don't say, okay, her Cohen status should go
away, but every Cohen is also a Levi. And why doesn't she
still have a לוויה Leviya status? Tosafot says no, you can't do
that. It's a package.
She doesn't have two statuses. She's both a Cohen and a Levi.
Her whole status is כהנת cohenet and if that is contradicted by
the sex with a non-Jew, then it is completely compromised. Yes.
If a כהן kohein has sex with, a male כהן kohein has
sex with a
non-Jew, right, or with a גרושה grusha or חללה challala or any
woman that he's forbidden, it does not affect his status. Right? It
is very one-sided.
The woman's identity is affected, not the man's. I mean, it's sort
of like part of the whole thing that.
And the children that he would have.
Oh, the children would be חללים. challalim. Right. The children would not
have קדושת כהונה. kedushas kehuna.
But they wouldn't be stigmatized any other way.
Oh, I'm sure they would.
Well, no, they wouldn't be. It's a big deal. No, it's a
big deal. But the point is they wouldn't be any worse off
than a ישראל. Yisrael. They wouldn't be any, right, correct. The children,
the product of that sexual act would, right, would, the children would
not have קדושת כהונה kedushas kehuna but they would not be further
stigmatized but. Well,
I mean, still walking around their whole life knowing that. I understand,
but the point, right, they're not כהנים. kohanim.
Okay. But they're not beyond that of a normal ישראל. Yisrael. That
of a normal ישראל. Yisrael. Yeah, no, but everyone knows their father's
a כהן. kohein. Their father's a כהן.
kohein. They're not. It is, it is, it is, but okay, relative
to what their parental status is, but they're not worse than a
normal ישראל. Yisrael. But Rivka's point is very well taken that it
goes to the same reality of the definition of adultery which is
defined by the woman and not by the man. And it's the
woman, the man can have multiple wives, can have sex outside of
marriage, even if he's married, the woman cannot. So the idea of
sort of of like the woman as more of the sort of
one who. She suffers very severely. I would call, yes, yes, she
suffers very severely. I wouldn't say that it's framed as a punishment,
but she suffers very severely. And it has to do with the
fact that she is more, I think it's part and parcel of
the whole fact that the man's sort of sexual freedom is much
broader and the woman's is much narrower.
But just so I understand, so if she is a כהנת, cohenet,
this very case here and then she is raped, then she can't
eat תרומה truma anymore? Correct. So let's say she's like a young
girl, what happens? What is she supposed to eat? Her father's a
כהן. kohein.
Her father doesn't only have תרומה, truma, you can sell תרומה truma
for the cost. It's not a good exchange rate, but you can
buy חולין. chullin. Okay. Yes.
And one question just tangential. Whatever happened to Dina after everything? You
never hear about Dina.
Yeah. We hear about her children. Yeah, we don't know. We heard
about her in the מדרש, Midrash, in the מדרש Midrash cited in
this week's last פרשה. Parsha. It was yesterday. Yesterday. No,
it says שמעון Shimon married her. שמעון Shimon married her. Yes. All
right. Move it on.
That's always your problem.
All right.
And the daughter was an Asenath. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So הניחא למר בריה דרב
יוסף משמיה דרבא ha nichla l'mar brei d'Rav Yosef mishmei d'Rava so
it cannot be the case of כהנת cohenet in our משנה mishna
cannot be the case of having had sex with a non-Jew because
then the child would have no כהונה kehuna status. And then we
have פדיון הבן? pidyon haben? Yes. So therefore what's the case in
our משנה mishna of כהנת? cohenet? הניחא למר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה
דרבא דאמר דעברה מישראל. ha nichla l'mar brei d'Rav Yosef mishmei d'Rava
d'amar d'ivra miYisrael.
If you say that it has nothing to do with the non-Jewish
father, even if the father was Jewish, and nevertheless you're exempt from
פדיון הבן pidyon haben not because the child has a כהן kohein
identity, but because the mother's כהונה kehuna status is enough to exempt
the child. ואו מוקי לה בלוי דעברה מישראל. v'u mukei lah b'Levi
d'ivra miYisrael. So
fine, it's a Jewish father. אלא לרב פפא במאי מוקי לה ela
l'Rav Papa bemai mukei lah
according to Rav Papa that says it only is when it's a
non-Jewish father that the כהנת cohenet mother is exempt. What's פשט? pshat?
Their non-Jewish father doesn't work for a כהנת. cohenet. So לעולם דעברה
מכהן. l'olam d'ivra mikohein. Fine, you're right. father's a כהן, kohen, that's
why he's exempt. So והיא בת ישראל, v'hee bas Yisrael, and she's
actually, she's not a בת כהן. bas kohen. So why does our
משנה mishna call her a כהנת? kohenet? ואמאי קרי לה כהנת? v'amai
karii lei kohenet? דבנה כהן, de'benah kohen, because it calls her a
כהנת kohenet because
her son is a כהן, kohen, meaning when our משנה mishna says
כהנת kohenet and לויה, l'viyah, their child is exempt, it doesn't mean
a בת כהן. bas kohen. It means the wife of a כהן.
kohen. When it says לויה, l'viyah, it means the wife of a
לוי. Levi. And you're right, because according to this explanation,
a בת כהן bas kohen would never exempt her child from פדיון
הבן, pidyon haben, from פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, because it would always
need a non-Jewish father and then it would completely compromise her status.
So anyway,
this is the question. There is that one opinion that says that
the exemption of the בת כהן bas kohen mother or בת לוי
bas Levi mother is very narrow. It's really only the בת לוי
bas Levi and only when the father is a non-Jew. We do
not rule that way. We say בת כהן, bas kohen, בת לוי
bas Levi exempts across the board because it's defined not only by
the father but also by the mother, and here's where the mother's
status actually does matter.
What do we actually say להלכה? l'halacha? Let's say a בת כהן
bas kohen is raped by a גוי. goy.
Yeah, that was never under debate. So let's take a look now,
top of מז ע"ב. Mem Zayin amud Beis. That's the issue about
the mother being a בת כהן bas kohen or בת לוי. bas
Levi. איתמר, itmar, now it was said. כהן שמת והניח בן חלל.
kohen she'meis v'hiniach ben challal.
So here you go. A כהן kohen had a son,
was married or had sex with a גרושה, grusha, let's say, and
the child is a חלל. challal. The child doesn't have קדושת כהונה.
kedushat kehunah. So in this case, here's a fascinating case. If
the mother is a
בת כהן bas kohen
and the father is a ישראל, Yisrael, the child is not a
כהן. kohen. But because the mother is a בת כהן bas kohen
and it's based on פטר רחם, peter rechem, there's no פדיון הבן.
pidyon haben. So even though the child isn't a כהן, kohen, there's
no פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Now in the flip case, the father's
a כהן. kohen. Well, it never, there the exemption is not based
on פטר רחם. peter rechem. There the exemption is based on the
fact that the child will be a כהן. kohen. But you can
have a scenario where the father is a כהן kohen and the
child is not. If the father has sex with a גיורת giyoret
or a גרושה, grusha, a divorced woman, the child is a חלל,
challal, as we were just talking about, does not have קדושת כהונה.
kedushat kehunah. So there the mother isn't a כהנת, kohenet, the father
is a כהן kohen but it doesn't matter because the exemption in
that case is not because of the father, the exemption in that
case is because the child is a כהן, kohen, but here he's
not a כהן. kohen. So in this case, the father who's a
כהן kohen is חייב chayav in פדיון הבן pidyon haben of his
son who is a
non-כהן. kohen. But now he died. While he was alive, he actually
didn't have to do it. Why? Because even though he was חייב,
chayav, basically he takes the five שקלים shekalim out of one pocket
and puts it in the other pocket. Fine. But now he's dead.
So what's the case? So let's take a look.
כהן שמת והניח בן חלל. kohen she'meis v'hiniach ben challal. רב חסדא
אמר, Rav Chisda amar, הבן
חייב לפדות את עצמו, haban chayav lifdot es atzmo, he has to
be פודה podeh himself. There's no father around to be פודה. podeh.
That would normally be a case where this happens, by the way.
Somebody actually has a child through a non-Jew or through who you
don't know who the father is or now we actually have cases
of artificial insemination or the father
died. As opposed to ברית מילה bris milah where if the father
isn't around, the obligation reverts to the community. According to one or
two ראשונים, rishonim, it goes first to the mother and then to
the community. That's by ברית מילה. bris milah. By פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben, if the father isn't around, the obligation reverts to the son
and to the person himself. And then only when he becomes an
adult, like בר מצוה bar mitzvah or whatever, then he's פודה podeh
himself. Which raises interesting questions about how do you remember thirteen years
in the future? Maybe set a reminder on your Outlook and hope
we're still using it thirteen years from now. Anyway,
that's ההלכה. ha'halacha. So here the first opinion is fine, he's חייב
chayav in פדיון, pidyon, the father isn't around, he has to be
פודה podeh himself.
Rabbah bar Huna says he's
effectively taking, well that's what we're going to discuss.
רבה בר הונא אמר, Rabbah bar Huna amar, אין חייב לפדות את
עצמו, ein chayav lifdot es atzmo, he doesn't have to. Now the
גמרא gemara will explain. כל היכא דמית אבא לאחר שלשים, kol heicha
d'meit abba l'achar shloshim, the obligation only kicks in when the son
is thirty days old. If everybody agrees that if the father died
after the son was thirty days old, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דאינו
חייב לפדות את עצמו, de'kulei alma lo pligi de'eino chayav lifdot es
atzmo, then he doesn't have to redeem himself. Why? שהרי זכה אביו
בפדיונו. she'harei zachah aviv b'fidyonu. On day thirty, or thirty-one, or whatever
the exact day is, he says, now I'm obligated, now I did
it. Like in that second, it's like he did it because he
just put the money in one pocket to the other. Now I
should point out by the way that we're going to get into
this starting on the next דף, daf, which is today's official דף,
daf, which is the interesting question about conceptually is פדיון הבן pidyon
haben about payment and is it about like דיני ממונות dinei mamonot
or is it about this ritual act of giving? Because you could
say that even though he's a כהן kohen and he could receive,
you need a ritual act of actually having given the money here.
Here it sounds like you don't need that. Here it sounds like
the very fact that it's a debt and the debt I could
pay to myself, I don't have to do anything. So we'll get
back to that question, but here it sounds like it's very much
focused on the debt aspect of it. So if it's day thirty,
just hold off, if it's day thirty, then you don't have to
do anything because then it already took place. So what are they
arguing about? כי פליגי היכא דמית אבא בתוך שלשים יום. ki pligi
heicha d'meit abba b'toch shloshim yom. He died before day thirty arrived
and before. ...before the father actually paid himself, so no payment has
ever been made. So in that case, רב חסדא אמר בן חייב
לפדות את עצמו, Rav Chisda amar ben chayav lifdos es atzmo, he
has to be פודה podeh himself. דהלא לא זכה אביו בפדיונו, dahalo
lo zachah aviv befidyono, the father himself never paid himself as it
were and no פדיון pidyon was ever done, so the son has
to do a פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. רבה בר אבונה אמר אין
הבן חייב לפדות את עצמו, Rabba bar Avuna amar ein haben chayav
lifdos es atzmo, he doesn't, דאמר ליה, de'amar lei, because he'll say
to any כהן kohen that would come to him, אתינא מכח גברא
דלא מצית לאשתעויי דינא
בהדיה. asina mikoach gavra delo matzis le'ishtuyei dina bahadei. Says I am
coming by virtue of somebody you could never have brought to בית
דין. beis din. Meaning, if my father, why am I חייב chayav
to redeem myself? It didn't start with me. The obligation started with
my father. Because he died, it reverted to me, but it started
with my father. You could never have brought my father to בית
דין beis din and collected from my father. He was a כהן,
kohen, he could have always just said I'm not giving you Mr.
somebody, you know, some other כהן, kohen, I'm giving it to myself.
So since you could never have collected the money from my father
and since my obligation derives from my father's obligation, it started with
him, it didn't start with me, therefore you cannot demand the money
from me. Okay, so that's how he understands this. Now, of course
that could be debated, and of course you could say two things.
First of all you could say the obligation didn't start with the
father if he died before thirty days, right? It never started with
him, even though had he been alive it would have been his.
That's number one. Number two, you could say that even if the
obligation sort of, you know, did sort of start with the father,
you could go point to the other point here, which is the
point I've been saying, which is that, you know, is that this
argument, well you couldn't have brought my father to a בית דין
beis din so you can't bring me to a בית דין, beis
din, is very much an argument in civil court. You know, you
can't sue me. You don't have the ability to sue me. But
what about the מצוה mitzvah of פדיון הבן? pidyon haben? If that's
like a ritual act, that's sort of being ignored, which is again,
the גמרא Gemara is framing this almost completely within the, treating פדיון
הבן pidyon haben as a pure ממונות mammonus civil type of an
issue, yes.
But someone who's doing a פדיון הבן pidyon haben can give the
money to any כהן, kohen, gets the right to choose.
Yes, but no כהן kohen because no, so because but because no
כהן kohen in theory, כהנים kohanim have a class, could, you
know, that's what's funny about framing it as a civil case, because
if it was a civil case then even in a normal case
no particular כהן kohen could demand the money from me, I'll say
I'll give it to somebody else. But here what it's imagining is
even the כהנים kohanim as a class could not demand the money
from me because I could say since you couldn't have demanded it
from my father and my obligation only derives from my father, you
can't derive it from me.
I don't understand that. I mean, so what? It started with father
but ended with him, you know? Right. Like if I, if I
finish building your סוכה, sukkah, you know, you didn't finish it and
I put the סכך schach on and I get the מצוה, mitzvah,
don't I? You know, so what's the difference in A, B? And
just to pick up on something else you said, you said it
was day thirty, thirty-one, which one is it?
We'll get to that.
Okay, but what about my first point?
Yeah, so that's the point is that you don't have because if
it's not a, I'm not directly obligated, meaning first you could ask
that question, right? When we say the father is obligated, is it
fundamentally the father's obligation and then if he's not around then it's
secondary, it's a derivative obligation of the son? Or you could imagine
it the other way, you could say fundamentally it's the son's obligation
but the son isn't old enough to do it, so therefore the
father does it on behalf of the son. You know, so you
could question how you even conceptualize that. But if you say it's
fundamentally the father's obligation, then you understand it. If you didn't have
a court case against my father, right, then how could you have
the basis of having a court case against me? I mean, it
changes. Maybe. Maybe,
but unless you understand that it's even if the obligation does change,
but if the obligation right now is only I'm, I'm satisfying my
father's obligation, then it's still framed as how it would be in
terms of my father. Anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara understands. But
you're right, that could be challenged as well. This is the question.
Let's take a look. For me, the overarching interesting point is that
it is being framed as a purely civil matter. Let's take a
look. תנן. Tnan. So now let's look at our משנה Mishnah to
see how that, what? Did I skip something? הכי גרסינן מזה
ובו
כבר?
hachi garsinan
mizeh u'bo kovar? No. Okay. Okay, תנן. tnan. נתגיירה. niskayerah. Line starting
with the word נתגיירה. niskayerah. It's about ten lines down, maybe
twelve. נתגיירה ומעוברת. niskayerah u'meuberes. Let's say a pregnant woman converted. בכור
לכהן. bechor lakohen. So the firstborn son is for פדיון הבן pidyon
haben because still, even though, even though let's say the, you know,
it was not related to the father because this is a case
that's not related to the father. The father was let's say a
non-Jew and let's say he converted with his wife and the pregnant
wife. Fine, but it's not his son for נחלה nachalah because it's
like they're, it's a new identity once they convert. But nevertheless, now
that they have converted, this woman is giving birth as a Jew
to her, to this child, and therefore that is, so gets פדיון
הבן. pidyon haben. So that's the case of when they converted as
when the mother was pregnant. בכור לכהן. bechor lakohen. דאמאי? de'amai? Why?
לימא ליה, leima lei, why doesn't the, so who are you going
to get the פדיון הבן pidyon haben from? From the son, not
the father. The father is no longer halachically the father, right? Because
he converted, he was a non-Jew and so on. So why do,
why are you entitled to get the פדיון הבן pidyon haben from
the son? לימא ליה, leima lei, let the son say to whoever
כהן kohen asks... asks him for it, אתינא מכוח גברא דלא מצי
למישיוני דינא בהדיה. Atina mikoach gavra delo matzi lishvunei dina bahadei. I'm
coming from a man you could never have—you could never have brought
to court. Meaning, who was my biological—you could never have gotten my
פדיון הבן Pidyon Haben from my biological father. My biological father first
was a non-Jew who wasn't obligated in פדיון הבן, Pidyon Haben, then
he converted, now he's a Jew, but as a Jew he's not
my father because he has a new family identity. So there's no
father you could ever have gotten it from, so you can't demand
the money from me, right? So why not? So you see that
that's not a legitimate argument. So the גמרא Gemara says, שאני עובד
כוכבים דלית ליה חייס. Shani oved kochavim d'leis lei chiyus. Non-Jew is
different because he has no—he was never related to the son, which
means what? Which means in that case where there was never a
recognized halachic father, then the obligation starts with the son. There the
obligation starts with the son, so you can't say you could have
gone to my father. But in our case, the obligation started with
the father. There was a halachically recognized father and then he died.
Okay, so meaning how do we conceptualize who's obligated in פדיון? Pidyon?
If there's no father, no halachic father, meaning a non-Jewish father, no
halachic father, or for example, an interesting example would be let's say
artificial insemination, right? So if there's no father, the obligation starts with
the son. If there is a father, it starts with the father
and at least according to this opinion, the son's obligation derives from
the father.
Do you know if in artificial insemination there is no halachic father?
That's a question, how do you deal with whether the sperm donor
is halachically the father. What were you saying? Michael, please. All
right, anyway, אמר רבי שמעון יאסינא, Amar Rabbi Shimon Yasina, so Rabbi
Shimon Yasina, interesting name, Joson, Jas, anyway, אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש,
Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, in the name of Shimon Lakish, כהן
שמת בתוך שלשים, Kohein shemeis betoch shloshim, so now we're going to
have the at least a conclusion of this debate, we didn't really
prove one way, כהן שמת בתוך שלשים והניח בן חלל, Kohein shemeis
betoch shloshim vehiniach ben chalal, so he died within 30 days and
his son is a non-כהן, Kohein, הבן חייב לפדות את עצמו, Haben
chayav lifdos es atzmo, he is obligated to redeem himself, שלא זכה
אב בפדיונו, Shelo zachah av bifdyono,
because the father did not already sort of do the פדיון Pidyon
by just being there on day 30. מת לאחר שלשים, Meis achar
shloshim,
after 30, אין הבן חייב לפדות את עצמו, Ein haben chayav lifdos
es atzmo, then he doesn't have to, שהרי זכה אב בפדיונו, Sheharei
zachah av bifdyono, then when it became day 30, the father was
a כהן, Kohein, it's like he automatically did the act of פדיון
Pidyon even by doing nothing, it's like he did it with himself,
and therefore the son does not have to. So the conclusion is
that the son cannot make this argument, 'Oh, you couldn't have brought
my father to דין.' Din. Now why could he have not? So
there's a lot of interesting conceptual reasons. One is maybe it's not
all about a civil case, there's also a מעשה מצוה, Maaseh mitzvah,
an act of giving the פדיון Pidyon even regardless of the civil
case. Or another possibility is is that the son's obligation when there's
no father, even if the father was alive and died, does not
derive from the father, maybe it becomes directly his obligation. So there's
a lot of interesting possibilities why we conclude the way we do,
but in the end we actually do say that the son is
obligated when the father died within 30 days.
Very quick question. Yes. I'm just not understanding why this is any
more—why this is like a definitive position for the אמורא. Amora. Now
an אמורא Amora says one thing, someone else in the other camp.
I don't understand why that—you're right, it doesn't prove the point, it's
just what one אמורא's Amora's conclusion was, and sometimes we say, you
know, if at a later generation there's no—you know, a consensus develops,
it doesn't prove it, it's just a question about what הלכה Halacha
becomes. Sometimes הלכה Halacha develops around a consensus position even if you
can't prove one way or the other. Okay, so now we finish
up the משנה. Mishnah. ובכלן בחמשה עשר אחר בעלה גמרו שלשים יום—so
Uvechulan bechamishah asar achar baalah gamru shloshim yom a woman got remarried
within three months of her first husband dying or divorcing, but either
way, and then the child—you don't—gets married, gets pregnant right away, or
whatever, has her child within the next few months, and you don't
know who the father is. So in that case, it's certainly this
woman's first child, so it's חייב בפדיון הבן, Chayav b'Pidyon Haben, although
neither father is going to do פדיון הבן Pidyon Haben because either
father will say it's not my son. Okay, so at least he
has to be פודה Podeh himself. But he doesn't get the double
portion because the brothers of each father will say you're not our
brother, and therefore he won't get a double portion.
But if there's no children from either of them, he's the only
one, does he get a double portion from both?
No, because then the uncles will say you're not the son and
it's our inheritance. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. בכור
לנחלה הוא דלא הוי? Bechor lenachalah hu d'lo havei? What, you're telling
me he just doesn't get a double portion? הא כפשוט שקיל? Ha
k'pashut shakil? The implication is that he would get like a normal
son? הא דמאי? Ha damai? How would that even work? Since there's
a question who the father is, they're going to try to cut
him out completely from the inheritance. ליזיל לגבי האי, Leizil legabei hai,
he'll go to one family, ולדחייה, V'lidchayei, and they'll push him away
and they'll say you're not our brother, ולגבי האי, U'legabei hai, he'll
go to the other family, ולדחייה, V'lidchayei, and they'll push him away
and they'll say you're not our brother, so he won't get any
inheritance, not just he won't get a double. So אמר רבי ירמיה
לא נצרכה אלא לבא אחריו. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah lo nitzrecha ela l'ba
acharayiv. Rabbi Yirmiyah, you're right, he's not going to get anything. What
we say, he's not the firstborn, we don't mean to say that
he gets a normal inheritance. What we mean to say is that
the next son is not going to be considered the בכור Bechor
either. והכי קאמר, V'hachi kaamar, בכור לכהן הוא, Bechor l'Kohein hu, he
is... this one that you don't know who the father is, a
firstborn for the כהן kohen because you know it's the firstborn of
the mother, והבא אחריו, veha'ba achrav, the next son, אין בכור לנחלה
ein bechor lenachla will not get the double portion because, meaning imagine
this, right? So you have one family, let's say you had a
guy with two wives here, a guy with two wives here. This
woman here, right, gave birth, right, you don't know, you don't know
whose, you know, whose son it is, whether it's Reuven's son or
Shimon's son. So then the other children that Reuven and Shimon will
have, even from other wives, right, it doesn't really matter, even they
won't also, even the firstborn there won't be the firstborn because maybe
this guy is the firstborn. Do you get it? This guy was
born first to both Reuven and Shimon. I mean, you just don't
know which one. And then they had other sons. So this guy
can't get any inheritance. But then you don't say, okay, so he's
out of the picture and then Reuven's next, Reuven's clear, the first
son that we know is his first son, you know, that we
know is his son, gets a double portion. No, because the other
brothers will say, maybe you're not the firstborn, maybe Shimon over there,
maybe that other kid was the firstborn. So therefore there's no first,
nobody gets a firstborn portion and this guy doesn't get any portion.
Is that clear? That's an... okay, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. So the גמרא Gemara says והבא אחריו אין בכור לנחלה.
veha'ba achrav ein bechor lenachla. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a
minute, וליכתבו הרשאה להדדי. velichtevu harsha'ah lehadadi. Why doesn't this child who
doesn't know who his father is get together with Reuven's first son,
Reuven's known first son, and say, listen buddy, they're not trying to
cut you out of your firstborn portion by saying I'm the firstborn,
but they're trying to cut me out of any portion by saying
I'm not their brother. They can't have it both ways. Let's give
each other a power of attorney. Okay, I'll give you my power
of attorney and you'll go and you'll sue the brothers and you'll
say, look, I'm entitled to my firstborn portion. Either I'm the firstborn,
and if you claim that I'm not the firstborn because that other
guy is your brother, then I've been given his power of attorney
and I'm going to sue you for the whole portion, for a
double portion. So therefore, that way they'll at least be able to
get one firstborn portion between the two of them. You got it?
Okay, so
וליכתבו הרשאה להדדי. velichtevu harsha'ah lehadadi.
Why don't they give, why doesn't the Reuven's other first, you know,
known first son together with this kid write, give each other power
of attorney and therefore they'll be able to at least get a
firstborn portion out of it? וכי תימא מתניתין דלאו
בהרשאה, vechi teima matnitin delav beharsha'ah, let's say you know what, in
principle that's true, but we happen to be talking that they didn't
do it, that they didn't give power of attorney. הא מוקמינא לה
כמאן דאית ליה הרשאה, ha mokmina lah keman de'it leh harsha'ah, later
we're going to say that we are talking about in another משנה
Mishnah with the idea of power of attorney. We'll get to that
when we get to it in tomorrow's דף. daf. So therefore you
can't just say we're not talking in those, that's not part of
the conversation. So let's say מסייע ליה לרבי ינאי. mesaye leh leRabbi
Yannai. So the reason they can't do this, they should be able
to, is proof to what רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai says. דאמר רבי
ינאי, de'amar Rabbi Yannai, הוכרו ולבסוף נתערבו כותבין הרשאה זה
לזה. hukru ulevasof nitarvu kotvin harsha'ah zeh lazeh.
Remember we said before
that the פסוק pasuk of יכיר yakir that it was significant by
בכור? bechor? And it has to do with when is a child
defined as the בכור, bechor, does it mean that the whole face
has to come out, you have to be able to recognize? So
we have another case about you don't know who the child is.
Reuven and Shimon, their wives are in the hospital and the babies
get mixed up, okay? And you don't know who's who. So they
make some deal who's taking which kid home. Fine, but at the
end of the day, you don't know who's who. Now, who gets,
neither of them are going to be able to inherit from their
fathers because everybody, all the brothers will say maybe you're the other
person. So let's, can they in this case also give each other
a power of attorney? Okay, so you get it? So Reuven's child,
questionable child, gives his power of attorney to Shimon's questionable child, and
Shimon goes to his brothers and says, look, I'm entitled to a
portion, either for myself or because I've been given power of attorney
by Reuven's kid, and vice versa. So can that work? Essentially the
same case. So here's what רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai says. He says
הוכרו ולבסוף נתערבו, hukru ulevasof nitarvu, if there was a moment where
you knew whose was whose child and then they got mixed up,
then כותבין הרשאה זה לזה, kotvin harsha'ah zeh lazeh, they can give
each other power of attorney because at least at that moment you
were defined as the son for inheritance because there was a moment
of יכיר, yakir, of being recognized as the father, who the son
was, who the father was.
Even if the father's not around?
Yeah. לא הוכרו ולבסוף נתערבו, lo hukru ulevasof nitarvu, if there was
never a moment, like it was all done in like רש"י Rashi
says it was in a cave, there was no light, you never
saw even for one minute who the mother
was, right, there was never one moment, so then אין כותבין הרשאה
זה לזה, ein kotvin harsha'ah zeh lazeh, then you are not, never
entitled to an inheritance. It's not just you're entitled but we don't
know. In order to be recognized as a son for purposes of
inheritance, there has to at least have been a יכיר, yakir, a
moment of recognition. So therefore, that's why you can't do a הרשאה
harsha'ah in our case. In our case, since this woman gave birth
and she never knew who the father was
because... Right, she remarried a man very soon after the other husband
died, there was never a moment of יכיר, yakir, and therefore you
can't solve it by power of attorney. So this is very important,
this is a major theme that comes up in בבא בתרא, Bava
Batra, which deals with inheritance, that the idea of who inherits very
much focusing on that word in the תורה Torah of יכיר. yakir.
Thank God for DNA. Exactly.
That's that's interesting. Would that suffice for a יכיר? yakir?
Could very well. I mean, yeah, I
mean, the question of do you need יכיר yakir at the moment
of birth, but presumably not, presumably not. Now DNA raises other problems,
there's a whole major discussion in פוסקים poskim about using DNA, because
if you start doing that, then it will we will find out
that there are a lot more of ממזרים mamzerim than we want
to acknowledge. So it raises serious issues about the use of DNA
in הלכה. halacha. Okay, anyway, moving on. אלו בכור לנחלה ולכהן. Eilu
bechor lenachala ulekohen. So now we're going to the category of somebody
who's a בכור bechor both for inheritance and for כהונה, kehunah, which
obviously you could just say any normal firstborn that's first to the
mother and first to the father. But that would be boring, that's
obvious. We want to give an interesting case about that. So המפלת,
hamapelet, so here's cases of after a miscarriage but a miscarriage that
does not change the mother's status, okay? It's not considered פטר רחם.
peter rechem. Basically, it's a miscarriage of a non-human fetus or not
sort of הלכתית halachically defined as human or of a non-developed fetus.
המפלת שפיר מלא מים, hamapelet shapir malei mayim, it is an embryonic
sac filled with water. מלא דם, malei dam, meaning no right, no
formed baby in there, no fetus. מלא דם malei dam or blood,
but again no
form, nothing is sort of has human form. מלא גוונים malei gevanim
or different colors, but again nothing that looks like sort of skin
what? גנינים? ganinim? I think גוונים. gevanim. Okay. המפלת כמין דגים וחגבים
שקצים ורמשים, hamapelet kemin dagim vechagavim shekatzim uremashim, or if there is
something there that has some form but it's not a human form,
it looks like fish or grasshoppers or other things. המפלת ליום
ארבעים hamapelet leyom arbaim or any or up to day 40, and
this is the importance of day 40, that the child is not
considered formed yet, very relevant for a whole range of הלכתי halachic
questions, the most obvious being issues around abortion. הבא אחריהם, haba achareihem,
after that, that is not yet considered to be a human fetus,
and therefore it is not considered פטר רחם, peter rechem, and a
child after that is still בכור לנחלה ולכהן. bechor lenachala ulekohen. So
he'll still be a בכור bechor for the firstborn for the mother
and obviously for the inheritance if it is the father's. But the
חידוש chiddush here is that for the mother's even though something was
expelled from her womb, it is not considered to be a human
fetus and therefore it does not change the status of פטר רחם.
peter rechem. This is even according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right?
Because the חכמים chachamim said
before in the
משנה mishnah of המפלת כמין אדם. hamapelet kemin adam. Right. Oh רבי...
no, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, would agree, this is before he disagreed
in the first place. Well yeah, no because he says that המפלת
כמין בהמה חיה ועוף. hamapelet kemin behema chaya va'of. Oh yeah, right,
correct.
This is even according to רבי מאיר, צדקת, tzadakta, right. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says... okay. Now יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen, here's
a very interesting case, Caesarean section, והבא אחריו, vehaba acharaiv, and the
one that follows
him, שניהם אינם בכור לא לנחלה ולא לכהן, shneihem einam bechor lo
lenachala velo lekohen, not for inheritance or for כהונה.
kehunah. Not for inheritance is bizarre. Why? It's still ראשית אונו, reishit
ono, it's still the father's firstborn. Why should it matter if he
comes out through normal birth or through Caesarean section? Now for the
for the כהן, kohen, you understand that the first one is not
פטר רחם, peter rechem, but you could argue well if the first
one wasn't פטר רחם peter rechem because it came out as it
were through the back door through the Caesarean, then the second one
would have to be פטר רחם peter rechem because that's the first
one that came out naturally, right? So you could... so guess what,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagrees with this. רבי שמעון אומר הראשון לנחלה
והשני לחמש סלעים. Rabbi Shimon omer harishon lenachala vehasheni lachamesh sela'im. Yeah,
the first one is still ראשית אונו, reishit ono, is the בכור
bechor for inheritance, he is the father's first son even if he
did not come out through natural birth. And the second one is
the first one that came that was the פטר רחם. peter rechem.
So yes, you exactly, both of them still have a status of
בכור, bechor, first for inheritance and the second for פדיון. pidyon. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. We rule like the
first opinion, although I think רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon just makes a
certain more intuitive sense. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
ראשון לנחלה לא? Rishon lenachala lo? Why, the first obvious question is
why does the one that's born through C-section not firstborn for inheritance
since that follows the father? So it says וילדו לו. Veyaldu lo.
The first we learn for inheritance is if a person has a
wife, it says וילדו לו בנים, veyaldu lo banim, and they give
birth to him children. So לידה leidah here is considered to mean
לידה leidah the natural way of childbirth. Okay. Right. It's פטר רחם?
peter rechem? According to this? What? לידה ופטר רחם? leidah u-peter rechem?
Yeah, basically they're the same thing. Right. Now תוספות Tosafot says it's
because it's a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah because when the... because this
is also there is also a debate when does a woman become
טמאה לידה. teme'ah leidah. When a woman becomes... you know, the תורה
Torah says that when a woman gives birth she becomes טמאה. teme'ah.
And there it says אשה כי תזריע וילדה זכר וטמאה שבעת ימים.
ishah ki tazria veyalda zachar vetame'ah shivat yamim. If a woman gives
seed and gives forth and then gives birth, then she will be
טמאה teme'ah for seven days. So that's the פסוק pasuk we focus
on to say not Caesarean section because it says עד שיולדה ממקום
שמזרעת, ad sheyoleda mimakom shemazra'at, only when she gives birth from the
same place the seed goes, the semen goes. woman seed goes, and
therefore meaning only vaginal birth and not cesarean section. So that and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagrees. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says like the
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon here that a woman is טמאה לידה tameah
leida even if it's C-section. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not have
that narrow definition of לידה leida like the חכמים Chachamim do. But
the same חכמים Chachamim that say that לידה leida is defined only
by natural by vaginal birth would also say here that the לידה
leida for inheritance, the word לידה leida learned from there means vaginal
birth. So that according to him, the חכמים, Chachamim, that is the
that defines the firstborn for inheritance. That's why they say now how
about לחמיש נמי לא? l'chamish nami lo? And he doesn't get obviously
he's not פדיון הבן pidyon haben when it's C-section. פטר רחם בעינן.
peter rechem beinan. It means through coming out through
the normal opening of the uterus, vaginal birth.
Now now how about the next guy? שני לנחלה לא. sheni lenachala
lo. The second guy certainly is not going to get בכור bechor
for inheritance. ראשית אונו בעינן. reshit ono beinan. It's not the father's
first child. So even though there was an exemption of the first
son because he was C-section, the second one is not the first,
so obviously he's not going to get a double portion. Now how
about the how about פדיון הבן? pidyon haben? He is the first
one that comes through the sort of vaginal birth, פטר רחם. peter
rechem. לחמיש נמי לא, l'chamish nami lo, why not for פטר רחם?
peter rechem? קסבר. kasavar. So that's a harder question, but because he
holds בכור לכל דבר אחד לא הוי בכור. bechor lechol davar echad
lo havei bechor. That you have to you cannot be only a
בכור bechor in one way. Now of course you can be a
בכור bechor in one way like you could be the mother's firstborn
and not the father's, and that is relevant for פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben, but you can't be in this question of here there's two
concepts in terms of like biologically what happened. There's the idea of
are you the first child to this mother and are you the
first one to come out through פטר רחם. peter rechem. And he
assumes that you need to be both aspects of firstborn. You cannot
be even though you are the first to be פטר רחם, peter
rechem, if you're not the first child of the mother, you cannot
be considered a בכור bechor for פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Okay, so
this is the argument of the חכמים. Chachamim. Again, we know why
the first one doesn't do פדיון הבן pidyon haben because it wasn't
born he wasn't פטר רחם. peter rechem. Why is he not inheritance?
Based on the word לידה, leida, they assume לידה leida means vaginal
birth. That's why the first one gets neither status. Second one certainly
is not for double double portion. He's not the father's first child,
but he's also not פדיון הבן pidyon haben because even though he's
the first one to come out פטר רחם, peter rechem, he's also
not the mother's first child. It's not enough to be the first
פטר רחם, peter rechem, you also have to be the first child.
Okay, so that's the position of
the חכמים. Chachamim. They divide equally in that case. Yes. Now let's
see what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. רבי שמעון אומר הראשון לנחלה
והשני לפדיון הבן. Rabbi Shimon omer harishon lenachala vehasheni lepidyon haben. רבי
שמעון לטעמיה דאמר תלי לרבות יוצא דופן. Rabbi Shimon letaameih deamar talei
lerabbot yotzei dofen. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that even when it
comes to a woman being טמאה לידה, tameah leida, even cesarean section,
a woman is טמאה לידה. tameah leida. His definition of לידה leida
includes cesarean section, and that's true for טומאה tumah and it's true
for for inheritance. So this first one that came out through C-section,
yeah, okay, that's included in the word לידה leida and therefore he
gets he's the double portion for inheritance. Now he doesn't get it
for פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. There it's not just about the word
לידה, leida, there the תורה Torah explicitly says פטר רחם. peter rechem.
And that opening the womb means the natural opening of the womb,
and therefore he does not get the double portion and he does
not get פדיון הבן pidyon haben because he was not the פטר
רחם. peter rechem. Now השני לפדיון הבן. hasheni lepidyon haben. And the
second one is the פטר רחם peter rechem and he does do
the פדיון pidyon on the second one. קסבר בכור לדבר אחד הוי
בכור. kasavar bechor ledavar echad havei bechor. Yes, and even though he's
only a בכור bechor for being the first to be פוטר רחם,
poter rechem, to come out through the normal opening of vaginal birth,
and he's not the mother's first child, it's the mother's second child,
that doesn't matter. As long as you are the פטר רחם, peter
rechem, that's enough. So for him he says, A, I don't in
general exclude C-sections from definitions of birth, number one, and therefore the
first son is בכור bechor for פי שנים pi shenayim for the
double portion. And in terms of פטר רחם, peter rechem, which is
about natural vaginal birth, that he says that would be
the first one that comes out that way even not the first
child is considered for פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. So that's רבי שמעון's
Rabbi Shimon's position. Makes a lot of sense. We don't rule that
way. We rule that if the mother has a C-section, that's it,
so it deals with no there's going to be no פדיון הבן,
pidyon haben, no double portion. It makes so much sense, why don't
we? What can I tell you? All right, now we actually get
to today's דף, daf, מ"ח עמוד א'. mem chet amud aleph. Let's
take a look. מי שלא בכרה. mi shelo bichara. Let me stop
and start again for that.